window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Relation",
  "duration": 69,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Relation",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>A relation \\(R\\) is said to be circular if \\(aRb\\) and \\(bRc\\) together imply \\(cRa\\).\n<br>\nWhich of the following options is/are correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>If a relation S is reflexive and symmetric, then S is an equivalence relation.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If a relation S is circular and symmetric, then S is an equivalence relation.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>If a relation S is reflexive and circular, then S is an equivalence relation.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>If a relation S is transitive and circular, then S is an equivalence relation.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>C.</b> <p>If a relation S is reflexive and circular, then S is an equivalence relation.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357408/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-43#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(R\\) be the set of all binary relations on the set {1,2,3}. Suppose a relation is chosen from \\(R\\) at random. The probability that the chosen relation is reflexive (round off to 3 decimal places) is ______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.125",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333214/gate2020-cs-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let G be an arbitrary group. Consider the following relations on G:<br><br>\nR1: \\(\\forall a,b \\in G, aR_1b\\) if and only if \\(\\exists g \\in G\\) such that \\(a=g^{-1}bg\\)<br>\nR2: \\(\\forall a,b \\in G, aR_2b\\) if and only if  \\(a=b^{-1}\\)<br><br>\nWhich of the above is/are equivalence relation/relations? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R1 and R2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R1 only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R2 only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither R1 nor R2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>R1 only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302838/gate2019-cs-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The time complexity of computing the transitive closure of binary relation on a set of n elements is known to be <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n * \\log (n))\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^{\\frac{3}{2}}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^{3}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^{3}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213532/isro2018-56\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The time complexity of computing the transitive closure of a binary relation on a set of \\(n\\) elements is known to be <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^{3 / 2}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^{3}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^{3}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128781/isro2017-80\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A binary relation R on \\(\\mathbb{N}\\times \\mathbb{N}\\)  is defined as follows: (a,b)R(c,d) if   \\(a \\leq c\\)\nor \\(b \\leq d\\). Consider the following propositions:<br>\nP: R is reflexive <br>\nQ: R is transitive <br>\nWhich one of the following statements is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both P and Q are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P is true and Q is false.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P is false and Q is true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both P and Q are false</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>P is true and Q is false.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39603/gate2016-2-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Let R be a relation on the set of ordered pairs of positive integers such that \\(((p,q),(r,s)) \\in R\\) if and only if \\(p-s=q-r\\). Which one of the following is true about R? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both reflexive and symmetric</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Reflexive but not symmetric</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Not reflexive but symmetric</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither reflexive nor symmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Not reflexive but symmetric</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8500/gate2015-3-50#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let R be the relation on the set of positive integers such that aRb if and only if a and b are distinct and have a common divisor other than 1. Which one of the following statements about R is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R is symmetric and reflexive but not transitive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is reflexive but not symmetric and not transitive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is transitive but not reflexive and not symmetric</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R is symmetric but not reflexive and not transitive</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>R is symmetric but not reflexive and not transitive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8089/gate2015-2-3#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider the binary relation R = {(x,y), (x,z), (z,x), (z,y)} on the set {x,y,z}.\nWhich one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R is symmetric but NOT antisymmetric</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is NOT symmetric but antisymmetric</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is both symmetric and antisymmetric</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R is neither symmetric nor antisymmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>R is neither symmetric nor antisymmetric</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/797/gate2009-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>A relation R is defined on ordered pairs of integers as follows:<br>\n(x,y)R(u,v) if x\\(\\lt\\)u and y\\(\\gt\\)v. Then R is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Neither a Partial Order nor an Equivalence Relation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A Partial Order but not a Total Order</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A Total Order</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>An Equivalence Relation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Neither a Partial Order nor an Equivalence Relation</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/883/gate2006-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Let R and S be any two equivalence relations on a non-empty set A. Which one of the following\nstatements is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(R\\cup S,R\\cap S\\) are both equivalence relations.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(R\\cup S\\) is an equivalence relation.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(R\\cap S\\) is an equivalence relation.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither \\(R\\cup S\\) nor \\(R\\cap S\\) is an equivalence relation.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(R\\cap S\\) is an equivalence relation.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1167/gate2005-42#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(R_{1}\\) be a relation from \\(A =\\left \\{ 1,3,5,7 \\right \\}\\) to \\(B = \\left \\{ 2,4,6,8 \\right \\}. R_{2}\\) be another relation from B to C = {1, 2, 3, 4} as defined below:<br><br>\ni. An element x in A is related to an element y in B (under \\(R_{1}\\)) if x + y is divisible by 3.<br>\nii. An element x in B is related to an element y in C (under \\(R_{2}\\)) if x + y is even but not divisible by 3.<br><br>\nWhich is the composite relation \\(R_{1}R_{2}\\) from A to C? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(R_{1}R_{2} = {(1, 2), (1, 4), (3, 3), (5, 4), (7, 3)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(R_{1}R_{2} = {(1, 2), (1, 3), (3, 2), (5, 2), (7, 3)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(R_{1}R_{2} = {(1, 2), (3, 2), (3, 4), (5, 4), (7, 2)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(R_{1}R_{2} = {(3, 2), (3, 4), (5, 1), (5, 3), (7, 1)}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(R_{1}R_{2} = {(1, 2), (3, 2), (3, 4), (5, 4), (7, 2)}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3645/gate2004-it-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider the binary relation: <br><br>\nS = {(x, y)|y = x + 1 and x, y \\(\\in\\) {0, 1, 2,...}} <br><br>\nThe reflexive transitive closure of S is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{(x, y)|y \\(\\gt\\) x and x, y \\(\\in\\) {0, 1, 2,...}}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{(x, y)|y \\(\\geq\\) x and x, y \\(\\in\\) {0, 1, 2,...}}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>{(x, y)|y \\(\\lt\\) x and x, y \\(\\in\\) {0, 1, 2,...}}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{(x, y)|y \\(\\leq\\) x and x, y \\(\\in\\) {0, 1, 2,...}}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>{(x, y)|y \\(\\geq\\) x and x, y \\(\\in\\) {0, 1, 2,...}}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1021/gate2004-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The binary relation S = \\(\\phi\\) (empty set) on set A = {1,2,3} is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Neither reflexive nor symmetric</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Symmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Transitive and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Transitive and symmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Transitive and symmetric</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/847/gate2002-2-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A relation R is defined on the set of integers as xRy iff (x + y) is even. Which of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R is not an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation having 1 equivalence class</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation having 2 equivalence classes</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation having 3 equivalence classes</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation having 2 equivalence classes</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/652/gate2000-2-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Let L be a set with a relation R which is transitive, anti-symmetric and reflexive and for any two elements  \\(a, b \\in L\\), let the least upper bound \\(lub (a, b)\\) and the greatest lower bound \\(glb (a, b)\\) exist. Which of the following is/are true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L is a poset</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L is a Boolean algebra</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L is a lattice</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L is a poset</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1481/gate1999-2-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>The number of binary relations on a set with n elements is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(n^2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^n\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n^2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n^2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1456/gate1999-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>The binary relation \\(R = \\{(1, 1), (2, 1), (2, 2), (2, 3), (2, 4), (3, 1), (3, 2), (3, 3), (3, 4)\\}\\) on the set \\(A=\\{1, 2, 3, 4\\}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>reflexive, symmetric and transitive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>neither reflexive, nor irreflexive but transitive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>irreflexive, symmetric and transitive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>irreflexive and antisymmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>neither reflexive, nor irreflexive but transitive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1675/gate1998-2-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(R_1\\) and \\(R_1\\) be two equivalence relations on a set. Consider the following assertions:<br>\nI.  \\(R_1 \\cup R_2\\) is an equivalence relation<br>\nII. \\(R_1 \\cap R_2\\) is an equivalence relation<br>\nWhich of the following is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both assertions are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Assertions (i) is true but assertions (ii) is not true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Assertions (ii) is true but assertions (i) is not true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (i) nor (ii) is true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Assertions (ii) is true but assertions (i) is not true</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1644/gate1998-1-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 20,
          "question": "<p>Suppose A is a finite set with n elements. The number of elements in the largest equivalence relation of A is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(n^2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n+1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(n^2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1643/gate1998-1-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 21,
          "question": "<p>The number of equivalence relations of the set {1,2,3,4} is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>24</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>15</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2259/gate1997-6-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 22,
          "question": "<p>Let R be a non-empty relation on a collection of sets defined by \\(_{A}R_ B\\) if and only if \\(A \\cap B = \\phi\\). Then, (pick the true statement) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A is reflexive and transitive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is symmetric and not transitive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R is not reflexive and not symmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>R is symmetric and not transitive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2731/gate1996-2-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 23,
          "question": "<p>Let R be a symmetric and transitive relation on a set A. Then <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R is reflexive and hence an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is reflexive and hence a partial order</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is reflexive and hence not an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2606/gate1995-1-19\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 24,
          "question": "<p>The less-than relation, \\(\\lt\\), on reals is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1993)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a partial ordering since it is asymmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a partial ordering since it is antisymmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>not a partial ordering because it is not asymmetric and not reflexive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>not a partial ordering because it is not antisymmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>E.</b> <p>none of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>E.</b> <p>none of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2303/gate1993-8-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 25,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following relations:<pre><code>  \nR1(a,b) iff (a+b) is even over the set of integers\nR2(a,b) iff (a+b) is odd over the set of integers\nR3(a,b) iff a.b &gt; 0 over the set of non-zero rational numbers\nR4(a,b) iff |a - b| &lt;= 2 over the set of natural numbers\n </code></pre>\nWhich of the following statements is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R1 and R2 are equivalence relations, R3 and R4 are not</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R1 and R3 are equivalence relations, R2 and R4 are not</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R1 and R4 are equivalence relations, R2 and R3 are not</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R1, R2, R3 and R4 are all equivalence relations</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>R1 and R3 are equivalence relations, R2 and R4 are not</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/695/gate2001-1-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
